few words about myself i'm ricardo
bragini and I'm chief System Architect
at the commodity I John I joined come in
2016 and prior to work at comma I worked
for about five years at Tesla I was
working on electric powertrain
technology and then in autopilot and
before that I did some research at the
State University for about one year on
electric vehicles I think a good way to
start talking about selling cars is to
introduce them by the 11th by the
Society the SAE divides self-driving
cars into five different levels so the
first level is a level one which is
level one well is what we can buy today
pretty much every new car that we buy is
considered level one the human is fully
in control of the car and the car
provides some driver of system features
so for example it can provide adaptive
cruise control so something that
maintains the distance with the car in
front
automatic emergency braking and lane
keep assist that allows you to go back
in the lane if you are if the car
detects that for example you are
strapped and you are departing the lane
but the point is you are fully in
control of the car and you're constantly
interacting with the car the next level
is called able to probably the most
notable example of level 2 system is the
test auto pilot and here the the
behavior of the car is completely
different the car is now fully in
control of driving and the driver when
the system is activated system watches
that the car is actually doing the right
thing so it's different we go from car
driving to the front from the driver
being fully in control to the car being
control and the driver assisting the car
the next step is is level trip I the
marked the transition to level 3 we do
it like a vertical line because here the
departing change like the main
difference is that the liability goes
from being from the driver from level 1
level 2 no matter
happens the driver is responsible for
driving from level 3 and above the car
is actually takes the responsibility
whenever they sell driving features are
active so what level 3 allows the driver
to do is allows the driver to be
distracted does not require the driver
to be ready to take over immediately and
it works a limited environment and it
always guarantees a few seconds of
safety operation even when the system
detects like a situation that cannot
handle so you imagine that you're
driving you are like reading a book or
reading your email the car detects
something that cannot handle then is
gonna beep at you and it's gonna still
perform safe operation for maybe 5 to 8
seconds that's what it's considered like
a good transition time and then you have
to take control
the next step is level 4 I think that a
good a good example like of level 4 car
C is what we see in from deployed from
way more like there are many other
companies
zooks or crew is GM they're all working
on level 4 so what level 4 is well if
taking the driver out of the loop like
let's take the driver completely out of
the car and let's have like a driverless
vehicle working in limited environment
the next example the next level is
called level 5 level 5 is devolution of
level 4 is likely before but instead of
working in with the environment is
supposed to work everywhere at any time
without a human so it needs to work at
least as good as human everywhere I
personally believe that it makes sense
I the two levels that are interesting
where people are working on are either
level 2 or level 4 and those are the
ones that we should pay close close
attention in the evolution of their
technology so what why do I say that
I like level 2 and level 4 are the most
important one well let's look at the
number so let's look at how many cars
like what are the distribution of the
levels on the cars today on the market
in United States it is 7.2 percent of
cars deployed like that we see on the
road today a level zero so they have no
assistance if you look around pretty
much like
one one in seven like six out of seven
cars that you see I have no assistance
at all then there is about like 12% of
cars that have level one so they have
limited assistance pretty much all the
new cars going to this category and then
there is about like a 0.2 percent of
cars that are considered level 2 I would
say the 0 2 percent is like in large
portion made by Tessa auto pilot and
like less less extent from like crew GM
and few other example that are popping
out from from automakers so what why do
I say that for example like level 3 is
not so interesting and I don't see level
3 being the next evolution like the next
step to us like a driverless future
well because level 3 by definition needs
to guarantee few seconds automated
driving we anything counter situation
that you cannot handle doing that is not
easy at all imagine that the system like
it's driving a highway at 70 miles per
hour
like maybe 775 and it encounter a
situation that does not how to handle
well doing safe operation for
five-second means that you travel pretty
much like more than a football field
doing doing and so yeah keep the car
doing something safe it's pretty much as
other solving for level four even if you
only have to guarantee those those few
seconds when the current counter
situation that you cannot handle well
you can say well yeah but it's true what
you're saying but there is one car that
actually shipped on the market the test
level 3 and it's true it's called a e8
is the Audi a8 it that it did not ship
us for regulatory reasons but let's look
at the limitation of such system so you
need to be on a multi-lane you order you
need to be you have to have bar in
between lanes so pretty much like on a
high-speed highway you need to have
structure along the edge to make sure
that there are no pedestrians your speed
needs to be lower than 37 miles per hour
and the speed of the surrounding
vehicles is also low
so the
this is almost impossible situation to
meet and it's not what level Terry's
supposed to be is just like an extension
of level two if something goes wrong in
this situation nothing bad can really
happen and so yes the car can take like
liability for the situation it does not
scale to situation like requiring faster
reaction time if you're driving highway
at high speed you you need to be able to
handle the situation and probably you
need like level four technology so what
about there before level so it's
interesting it's an interesting
technical challenge there are a lot of
companies working on it but what woody
is live at four what does level four try
to solve that well let's think about it
which is the definition of likely before
so like we have level four car so how do
they work
well the idea is that they allow you to
go from point A to point B without
requiring you to drive and if you think
about it these already exist like the
taxi there uber I can I can use public
transportation so they're trying to
replace a service that already exists
it's not gonna be more practical it's
not gonna be more practical the rubber
is not gonna be more practical in
certain cases in the public
transportation if you live in Manhattan
you want to go from point A to point B
probably taking the metro is the best
way to do it so what's the advantage of
living for well the Vantage is the idea
that they are going to cost less why
because the idea is to remove the driver
and to remove the cost of the driver
which I personally have some some doubts
by when you pay dry you will drive it's
not a big portion of your fare that goes
to the driver the big majority pays for
the car maintenance their insurer gas
and the fees to Ober so level four by
definition since it's not supposed to
drive anywhere anytime
does not compete with Kenosha P is that
meant when the car ownership but this
idea that whenever four succeed the
people we stop owning cars so it's just
not what level four is going to give us
and it was like very unclear how long
such a service will take to be better of
uber lyft public transportation in terms
of cost and practicality so what about
level five like I said I when I show the
slide before about the levels I didn't
show any example of companies working on
level five because literally nobody is
working right now on level five it's
very our problem those are two famous
quotes that I usually put in my
presentation one is from Iran in 2016 he
said that in about two years someone
which is the function that is supposed
to call your car out of your garage that
is working you press a button in the car
like slowly crawl out of your garage
well he was predicting there in 2016 and
in about two years so 2018 the car was
able to have this function working from
New York to LA for example so he was
imagining a future in 2018 where a car
could drive completely without human
intervention without a driver in the
seat from New York to LA and another
quote is from Chris Armstrong back it
was like the ex chief of the cell
driving from a Google before he became
way more and it was respecting that his
son which was 12 was not gonna need a
driver license by the time that he was
going to be 16 that was in 2015 his son
was 12 now I'm pretty sure he's more
than than 16 years old and I'm pretty
sure he got his driver license why why
it's actually like our to to solve
before for level five and nobody's
working on it
well it's very it's very challenging
problem you have to solve for situations
that are very hard to train a system for
a new man are very good at it
because they actually use like things
that they have learned outside driving
the first time that I drove a car myself
I did okay how come if I never drove a
car well I did okay because I was I was
actually I was actually transferring the
learning that I did outside
driving to to driving itself so how much
of of driving is actually you
skills that have nothing to do with
driving it's possible that to be able to
replace the driver entirely in any
situation you might need some sort of
like artificial general intelligence
systems being developed first and so
this is this is something that it's
definitely gonna take a while and I
don't see it being like in a closer eye
so while it will chew that well so
what's interesting about I will show is
people spend five percent of the awake
time driving and while you drive you
pretty much take and one action of
compacting the gas core I think the
brake or correcting the steer pretty
much every second so if you dry for
about like 20 hours like three hours so
straight that's about 10,000 single
intervention that you have to make to
your car and that's actively stressful
another thing that is worth noticing is
that there have been last year to the
seven fatal accidents in the u.s. that's
an increase of 15 percent from the
minimum reach in 2014 this is like quite
interesting because an unfortunate
because for many decades fatal accidents
in US have been going down the reason
why has been going up since 2014 is that
people are more distracted while driving
they look more therefore and
unfortunately this made more fatal
accidents and so there is really the
need of making sure that there's a
system monitoring the driver paying
attention so another very important
thing to know is and this is great if
there's a level 1 cache on today so
pretty much every New Castle today
already have the hardware to be a level
2 system to constitute to our level 2
system like if you think about every one
cars since they're capable of
maintaining distance for the car in
front of you are able to steer you back
in the lane if you are about to depart
the lane it means that they had ways of
controlling the gas the brake and the
steer and so those those actuator can
actually be controlled in a better way
not only to provide level 1 features but
actually level features the reason why
cars that we see on the market today
have only level 1 features and not level
piñon is because of cars are developed
with a very long development process
it's not possible to make over-the-air
update in pretty much like every car on
the market today
except for Tesla and the car the car
like the arguer that makes your chassis
like your actuators is very integrated
with the arguer that makes your
computing and the software that comes
with the car and if you think about the
lifespan of a car average lifespan of a
car is 15 years think about how much
like computing and computers have
changed in 15 years so I do believe
there is this need to decouple the
armour of the cars like what was the
chasm was your actuators and was like
what makes the hour before you can from
your computing hardware which is what
actually makes your your
driver-assistance features so well in
order to the sky whatever to is we can
just look at the video this is this is
our system that we developed at comedy I
if you can see the system itself like
they are where is mounted on the
windshield it connects with the can
which is the communication system off of
the car and this is retrofitting a
level-one car which is a 2016 conceal so
how does a level-two system works well
so the idea is that you press a button
you engage and then the car handles
driving for you you have to pay
attention but the car will keep in the
lane will slow down will accelerate
depending on traffic conditions and
other information that they can gather
from the environment so it's very
different way of driving of course as
the system gets better it's very
important that the driver keeps paying
attention and so every level to system
as the level to system gets better it's
very important to monitor the diver and
so in our system this is done by a
camera that is also watching the driver
so there are two cameras one looking at
the road and one watching the driver so
how does driver monitoring works so the
idea is that the camera is watching you
and
if you for example while driving you're
being distracted so you're looking away
from the Honda or for example you're
falling asleep or anything the system
detects that you are not looking
straight then the system is gonna start
to alert you it's going to start to beep
at you and then eventually if you don't
take control the system goes into a mode
where it's gonna force you to disengage
the automated feature and it's gonna
slowly bring down the car to a safe stop
so how does like self-driving car works
like before introducing and talking
about data let's spend a few few words
about how an architecture or some
driving car is well you might have seen
this before it's a very standard kind of
like layout of the system working in a
in a self-driving car but more in
general in manual bollix systems so you
have an initial like your input comes
from your sensors you use sensors to to
sense the world instead of in cars the
sensor typically cameras liders rather
ultrasonic sensors and all the sensor
that you use to perceive the state of
the car itself like accelerometers
gyroscopes and like magnetometer GPS to
understand your positions and so once
you have the data form from the sensor
what you use them for well two things
one is you localize yourself you
localize yourself in in the world
reference this is very important because
well if you if you are working towards
like a system with a car like drives
itself it needs to be aware of your
position to better Drive you why the
system is active and it also uses the
input from the sensor to make a semantic
representation of the environment
you go from a dense sensor output for
example for cameras you have these like
million of pixels in RGB format so it's
very dense it's very it's very high
dimensional output to something that you
compress
and you extract information that then
you need that people know how to
interpret and then you need to keep
going with your flow of operation so in
to make some example in still driving
cars so usually the the perception layer
determines where lane lines are where
cars are and we all the values obstacle
on the road are so then you use this
input to your next block which is called
planning so once I know we're like
obstacle ours I understand my
environment in a semantic way then I can
plan for it I can generate a trajectory
that I want the car to take once once I
have the trajectory I actually have one
last block which is called controls and
if the block the heart weighs the car
physically activates the car to make
sure that the car follows your plan good
news about the current state of
self-driving cars and sensor
localization this is already at
superhuman level like you can put as
many camera and as many sensor you want
around the car you can have at any given
instant perfectly under 60 view of your
surrounding human of course have to turn
their head and they you have to
sacrifice some field of view while they
are looking around in selling cars this
is not necessary you can put as many
sensors as you want and the localization
is also super human I mean like for
example like last year we drove around a
closed track without using any any
vision input just by using our GPS and
doing a sensor fusion with with the
sensor on the car like accelerometer and
gyroscope and we were able to
continuously loop around the track
without having any sensor and we add
like I would say probably a precision of
less than one meter like less than three
feet in place in understanding where the
car using what the reference this is
already superhuman like human of course
don't understand where they are in world
reference which such accuracy controls
are good enough
they are definitely better than human
when they work in their specific domain
of
operation where they have been developed
for they don't work or like they're a
little bit trickier to have them work as
good as human when the condition
suddenly changed so imagine that you're
driving and all a sudden you eat a bump
or your steering gets misaligned well
then you have to have a Largo a to
understand that for you driving straight
means applying a little steering on the
side well so this is you have a lot of
the situation that you need to handle
and and you know the situation is a bit
trickier and I think human can do these
currently better than machines so
adapting to sudden change of your model
but I I think what Russ I could
definitely like pros and cons with
respect to human and they are good
enough it's now resorting back to
driving cars the thing that are like
highly subhuman human do better than
machines is a sense of fusion and
perception implanting suspicion
perception like understanding the
semantic representation of the world
human are better these typical examples
there is a long tail of events where
shell driving car have a little bit hard
time handling them so imagine like you
see a plastic bag tumbling on the road
well so that I mean car might recognize
that there is like an obstacle but then
you have to decide is this something
that I can eat or is this something that
I should break for and this decision
becomes very important if you're driving
at 65 70 miles per hour down the highway
planning is also is also very hard the
way that human things like planned their
trajectory
I personally believe as I was saying
before it has more to do with skills
that not necessarily people have learned
from from driving but things that they
just understand they have some sort of
like intuition about the physics of the
world they just apply and they generate
those trajectory and it's very are the
creating algorithms at the base so maybe
a better approach which is what we are
torturing at , is putting together and
try to solve at once sensor fusion
perception planning all some sort of
like more like an end-to-end approach
and I think this is gonna scale better
than trying to separate these two blocks
so what are they
useful for well that are useful for
improving those those two blocks because
they do need machine learning a machine
learning can work with with data so
let's talk about data why are they
important in in cell driving cars well
of course first first thing is to train
your network so you have you collect
your data you collect your data from
your devices from your fleet and then
based on the behavior or the correct
behavior that the car took on the road
you try to train your network that
understand how to drive as they got from
the example of driving another thing why
data is important is that you can use
data to build your own HD Maps this is
an example of our of the maps that we
started to build based on our data you
can in this case we generated a cloud
point data set that for example
described the very poor Aging in the Bay
Area and this is important because
having these informations helps you
localizing very precisely in water
reference when when you're driving data
is also useful to simulate Andy bargain
when you can let back data from from
your fleet you can you can use this data
to see what happened and you can resume
elate the data you can you can use
messages are one of our debugging tool
and you can actually a play part of your
code on the data that you collected to
see how for example some changes of your
code will affect the part of the data
part of the output it was that was
actually collected and then of course
you wanted to collect it in case of cell
driving cars adventure if you offer a
service to your users at the product
that we sell is called the chameleon is
the device that I will show that I shown
before in the video and it also work as
a smart dash camera so you have cameras
you can collect data to the cameras and
of course like the user can have access
to their own data and we built our own
like Explorer so if you are like a comm
you
user then you can go on explore the
common CI and review your drive and
everything that happened so one thing
that's important to talk about is also
the cost about data collection because
we talked about the benefits and someone
might have the idea or like the the
impression that more data is better well
you have to consider also that there are
costs associated to data and it's not
always true that more later is better I
think good a good plot is the one on the
right which separates between companies
that have a like a product in the field
and they can collect their data through
the product that they saw the versus
companies that actually have to make
their own fleet and they you have to pay
in order to collect data I mean if you
if you think about how much it has like
a how much like individual profit maybe
Tesla can make on each car and you work
out the math I believe that Tesla makes
money for each mile that they collect
because it means that they stole more
cars and I would say like same way is
true for us the more miles we collect it
means the more devices we have solved
this is definitely not true for
companies that are working on level 4
they have to make their own cars they
have to make their own devices and you
have to pay drivers at least one in some
cases even to that at any given time
that I scare around and you have to pay
basically for their salary and so if you
think about the matter how much you pay
each driver but it costs to level four
companies about I like estimate these
are my estimates I estimate that they
pay about 2.5 dollars about two point
five dollars per miles if you think that
companies like way more connect pretty
much the same amount of miles that we
collect I believe it's around several
tens tens of thousands of miles each day
well if they paid two point five dollars
x let's say totally thousand miles
there's about 70 thousand dollars per
day that throughout here that's like
about like 21 million dollars and yeah
it's the budget you used to have deep
pockets
if you are owning like 11 for Fleet then
you are collecting data through your own
fleet another thing that you have to
consider is like connectivity in Casta
you have these devices that collect your
data how do you get data back well if
you own your fleet this might be a
little easier because the car gets back
and you you basically can can stream
back the data using like physical
connection but for our distributed
devices yeah we can use Wi-Fi but it's
very convenient for users if can
actually upload their data through
cellular connection so a connection is a
cost and so these must be considered
when you when you when you stream back
data to to your database data center
other thing that has cost if you use
data for bit for training in machine
learning you have to label them and the
label is something that is generally
done by humans so you have to teach
what's right to your neural network and
so you do these by having like usually
done by having like humans like taking a
picture and telling and like taking
notes wearing the picture of things are
what everything in the picture is in
this case where cars are where orders
lane lines buildings etc will come move
completely away from human labeling and
we try to do everything automated so we
use neural networks to label data that
we used to train other neural network
another thing that if it's like that you
pay for is of course processing training
and data transfer if you have your data
stored on the cloud and you're like oh
the Descent you do spend on data like
processing your data you spend
electricity to train your data because
they run on GPUs and you do Spanos data
for data transfer if you go if you have
you audit on the cloud you have to
transfer your data to something like an
eventual if you want to train luckily
and this also has a cost and probably
the most important thing is the cost of
storage the data one thing that a camera
we quickly realized is as the number of
users that we have keeps growing we saw
that I really like steep increase in
storage cost if you think about it and
if you assume that the number of users
that you have it's sort of like growing
linearly over over time well think about
how much storing their data indefinitely
is going to cost you I mean generally if
your function of user increase is called
f of X where X is your time well they
can't the cost of storing their data is
the integral of of f of X because you
have to store their data all date a new
data over time and so no matter what
your business model is in the case of
the driving cars where data are
particularly expensive because in our
case every hour of driving is between
five and ten gigabytes in the case of
level-4 car so I would not be surprised
if every hour of data it's gonna be
hundreds of gigabytes well you're gonna
quickly start to skyrocket your your
cost of storage if you don't act on it
and you don't start like to delete all
data as your user base actually grows so
some some tips about that data storage
and use of data I think unless you have
as I said before like a lot of lot of
money people are invested money on you
and you can build your own fleet and you
can you can afford of paying tens of
billions of dollars per year in that
collection
think about making a sustainable
business model around collecting data
early on in your stage so in case of
comma the first product that we actually
released with a dash cam app you could
download from the App Store or from
from the Google store Google Play you
could not load our app which was called
shiver and it's a dashcam and through
the tap we were collecting data the app
was free but at least we didn't have to
pay for for every day that we collected
the second product that we released is
was generator
it's a nobody to dangle it's called
panda and this is the first time that we
started to make a profit with a product
so by syncing your app with the kanri
they're not only we add back vision like
camera data from from from the car from
your phone but also we were able to sync
the data with your can with all the data
that was running onto your communication
area network which is the protocol of
communication of your car and this was
great because we could like seeing what
the cow everything that was being
recorded from the sensor of the car
together with the video data coming from
your phone and then we evoluted into the
product that you are currently selling
which is called the chameleon it's a
smart dashcam
it's something that you can install on
the wishes of your car by default it
provides a passive driver assistance
features and with passive I mean
warnings so in the text if you are
instructed it warns you if you are about
to collide and then of course it
provides all the functionality of a
dashcam but at the same time is also a
completely open development platform
which can be coupled with our open
source software which is called open
pilot and so it does support open pilot
and open pilot is the software that I
show you before in the video that can
actually like drive your car I don't
think that you you might want to to
consider about about data is I think if
the cloud services is worth it like is
it worth storing storing your data on on
the cloud is definitely a good starting
point which is where like we started as
comma we we started to upload all our
data on the cloud also cloud services
like companies that provide cloud
services are very good in giving you
some
sort of like intro grant where basically
you basically use their service for free
up to certain amount of expenses and
this is a great starting point but then
as your user grows if you really don't
have like a back-up plan or a way to
continue your cost you'll find yourself
once you run out of the free money
provided by the cloud service that you
are going to spend after that a very
high monthly cost because as I said your
user grow is growing quickly and so
consider that keeping your data on the
cloud is actually a good thing
especially if you use your data for
training and you want to stop like using
for structure to transfer that around
maybe actually transfer it luckily it's
a good solution and we definitely
thought it was a good solution for us we
did the math
buying our hard drives allows us to
repay the cost of the cloud in about two
months of course we don't have the same
redundancy that we have on the cloud but
at the same time as I said before our
users keeps going and so for us there is
no much value in today's data there is
more value in the ability of collecting
new data select and upload only the data
that you need currently a camera we are
uploading all the data from users but
will soon start to think about well
maybe not all the data so relevant
most of the data about driving is
somewhat boring it's about driving
straight on the highway and after you
have enough date of these maybe you
don't need any more data and instead you
can select your own data based on
certain criteria that you define at any
given time it could be for example any
time that the user intervene any time
that the user corrected the action of
your system is very interesting data
because it means that somewhat your
system failed to do something right and
so that's useful data or maybe like
turns or maybe adverse climate
conditions etc and ultimately disease
for some psychological reasons they
companies tend to keep around data that
they don't use my recommendation is
discarded in you de news as you progress
in your hardware you'll have legacy data
legacy
means data that you are not using it's
incompatible with newer data and so
instead of keeping it around and
thinking maybe I will find a use of them
in the future
think about that you are paying a
constantly a monthly fee for them and
maybe like a better idea is is discard
data that you don't use don't keep that
around if you don't have a good use for
them at any given time thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
yeah definitely I think level level five
cars anything the reason I need to call
them level six I think level five car so
we actually be very similar to what what
you described when they're gonna be
applied I think a lot of it will be
around like entertaining it's pretty
much like flying like the idea of giving
entertainment to the driver I mean we
start to see maybe I mean we see a
little bit of these like in cats when
you take a taxi you have some taxi you
have like like you can watch a video in
front of you and I definitely see this
way more like passenger center like
those like level five vehicles being
deployed in this way I don't know like
yeah it's gonna be interesting I think
the first deployment of level four is
probably gonna be retrofitting existing
cars building new cars is very hard
getting like the good reliability Zarda
and it's a lot easier to retrofit
existing existing models with with the
other and there and the sensor that you
need but then out like the technology
progressed and I do believe that cars
are going to be optimized around the
customer experience definitely I think
we're out of time okay thank you
[Applause]
hi everybody welcome to the fireside
chat so today over the last few days
we've been listening to experts talk
about machine learning AI
and applications to different industries
and I hope you've enjoyed the sessions
for the last few days now we're gonna
kind of deep dive into autonomous
vehicles um the hype and the impact in
the industry and so I'm going to let
would you like to introduce yourself
again yeah definitely so my name is
Ricardo Vizzini
and I'm with the commodity I I joined
come in 2016 and I'm chief systems
architect and prior to come I worked at
Tesla on the autopilot system and
on the development of electric power
trains and before that I worked on
researching electric vehicles at the IU
State University
so autonomous vehicles and and automated
vehicles let's talk about let's start
out with definitions just level set and
I'm sure some of y'all were at this
session this morning but for the
newcomers yeah I think a good way as I
mentioned we have any presentation for
the people that we rank here for the
presentation it's important to
distinguish between levels of automation
the sae defines the five different
levels level 1 2 3 4 and 5 and level 1
is pretty much like the car some assist
the driver so the driver drives all the
time but the car make makes intervention
and makes driving safer and easier in
level 2 because the car is full in
control of driving and the driver
actually assists the car and an example
is Tesla Tesla vehicle GM supercruise
and what we develop a comet the eye and
then from level 3 and above the driver
is not responsible anymore
the car is responsible for for the
driving actions so the driver is not
required to pay attention at all time
with level 3 the driver is only required
to take control of the car after a few
seconds of safe operation of the vehicle
when the vehicle encounters a situation
that cannot handle and then for 11 4 & 5
is driver is completely driverless
vehicle and in level 4 is limited
environment in level 5 is full full
automation in unlimited environments so
basically making a robot that can drive
as good as a human when when are they
coming into the market yeah I mean it's
a good question and the answer is
certain certain levels of automation
already here level level 1 is what you
buy today if you buy a new car and in
you're on the new to your author like
the most popular cars have 11:1
automation a few cars on the market and
represent about the 0.2 percent
the fleet today in us are level two
mainly our test autopilot and then there
is no like release the car in u.s. that
is like level 3 or above and so when
when are those car comings when I would
say first we should we should try to
increase the number of cars on sublevel
2 how do we make the existing cars like
smarter how do we how do we make the
fleet how do we change the fleet
incremental ii and i would say the
natural like way that it's going to
change is cars are gonna transition from
level 1 to level 2 and then when level 4
level 3 4 & 5 are gonna be applied well
I would say like I would said before in
the presentation I think one interesting
level that we should be paying attention
to is level 4 level 3 does not make much
sense because solving for level 3 is
pretty much as I have a solving for
level 4 guaranteeing this certain amount
of time of safe operation it's not it's
not simple task and solving for that is
as our in my opinion solving for level 4
so what what we are going to see at
certain points is the deployment of
fleets that work in limited environment
and with driverless vehicles that can
bring you to point A to point B so
hopefully we are going to see that in
the near future but these level 4 does
not compete with level 2 level 4 what
level 4 aims to is the replacement of
existing services such as uber such as
Poli transportation is just meant to
make those services cheaper by removing
the driver from from the loop conference
I work in the automotive aftermarket and
one of the things I do is I watch the
car park and watch how it's changing and
and how it's gonna be changing the next
15 20 years to keep my company
competitive so when I thought so od BC
connectors oh we need two connectors
those are the little you stick something
under your dash used a lot for some
basic diagnostic functions that that
it's not smart enough that's not
connected and the right way to make it
make my dumb car into a level 2 car no
yeah so what we do at karma and it's
taking existing car so so proving that
level 2 technology can be applied to
existing cars you can take any new cars
to tell level 1 capability and we prove
the individual that I showed you a
representation that you can actually
turn it into a level 2 car because a car
that are new and comes out today have
already backed waiters and a way of
communicating of controlling that
waiters such as gas brake and steering
in a way that you can actually have the
car driving itself if it is marked
enough it has the right software and
then I compute so yeah I mean like if
you the way that you interact with the
car is tapping into the can system of
the car and it can be done through video
pores or it can be done from any under
and present in the car the technology
needed to really hit the level 2016 well
you eat the you need to do you need
actuators you need they are the weather
comes with the car be ready to be to be
upgraded basically so you need pretty
much like a new car so from 2016 above
but really in 2019 almost an in your car
could be could be retrofitted way to
meet a level 2 in theory does anybody
want to guess what percentage of the car
park is 2016 and above anybody who's
brave you're pretty close it's 20% so
that also means that right now we have a
lot of dumb cars on the road that won't
be able to have the full benefit of you
know some aftermarket accessories
there's still some programming you can
do through there's lots of obd2 port
platforms so for the novice car person
who knows just enough Python to get in
trouble and github x' that can help you
get there but it doesn't take it quite
to where it's the driver assist and have
the functionality to
if you want the car to actually be
driving itself you need you need
basically access to to that to eight
hours so the age of the vehicles is
another thing that age of the car park
has been something interesting that
people in the aftermarket have been
watching because people are holding on
to cars way longer
in 1996 the average age of the car who
is eight point five years and you had
you had it on the slide earlier just in
the the current age according to IHS of
an average car in America is eleven
point seven years and it's been
predicting to increase even when there
have been movements like the cars cash
for cars that only took six hundred and
seventy thousand old cars off the roads
so yep there's one challenge I think
you're gonna have is getting around
those dumb cars well so definitely those
cars those cars like are gonna be around
for a long time and it's highlighting
one important fact that is if the
average life of car is about like to be
to twelve years and it's actually like
increasing over time there is really
this need of the coupling the hardware
of the comes with the car so the car
itself like the chassis actuators those
are not meant to last maybe fifteen
years or more from the part from the
brain of the car that should be
something that instead we should be
treating as consumer electronics should
be something that we should be able to
replace update and I'm not talking just
about software updates or software
updates which none of the car that's all
today except for Tesla is capable of
doing it but I'm also talking about like
being able to replace the computing
hardware in the last fifteen years if
you think about cars fifteen years ago
and you think about cars today you don't
I I don't think it the perception of the
change of this car has been like so big
like still has four wheels they cost
pretty much about the same amount of
money and they serve pretty much the
same purpose what's changed is the cost
of computing particular like GPUs they
reduce the cost of computing in the last
fifteen years by Toyota of magnitude so
if ten thousand times cheaper has
buying GPU so having the same computer
today that it was 15 years ago and so if
you think about it well why I think
about cars that you buy today and think
about them in 15 years from now how
outdated they will feel an analogy that
I make it's like you are buying a house
and you are not allowed to replace the
washing machine
that's how cars are going to feel when
you buy them now and they are not
structuring the capital in the proper
way so this is what we're trying to
solve , we try to make a feasible key
that can work with your existing car and
you treat it as a consumer electronic
you treat that device that you install
on the windshield connects with the can
system of your car with something that
after maybe every two years when a new
system comes out you can replace it
there is there is really no reason why
you should replace the old car to have
better driver system features and that's
also what we're seeing partnerships
we're seeing large autumn automobile
manufacturers partner with different
technology company to start treating the
technology in the car more like a
consumer electronic and that way you can
have that upgrade ability and as you
mentioned before Tesla's the only one
who does over-the-air update so it does
require some you know handling and care
to get the data updated but change in
perspective like that is going to help
treating it like the development cycle
for electronics I think will help keep
you happier when you have your eleven
point seven year old car in a few years
yep let's see so issues with driverless
you talked this morning about data
collection is there how did how data
collection using your tools so is that a
limitation still for three and four the
higher-end cars and commercial are there
pictures available if we're talking
I mean commercial vehicles comes up to
that was very yep lots of you know
magazine covers with being a fully
electric 18 wheelers how close are we to
their well okay so I think the
distinction needs to be made between
data collection that is made through
like devices and product that are
current results so if you work on level
two like for example
Tesla tells us the ability of collecting
everyday 4 million miles like they have
enough car that everyday they can
collect 4 million Minds a comma we are
we are about thirty thousand miles per
day that we can collect and so if you
have a product that you actually sell it
becomes a lot easier to collect the data
and you can actually be a little bit
spoiled by the amount of data that you
can collect
you can select you can decide which data
to upload that you don't need to upload
all the data definitely test is not
uploading four million lines of data
every day so if you work on like level
tree evolve on something that has not
been released yet to the public then you
cannot collect this data from from
people from your device that are out in
the field but it's also important to
distinguish between which type of data
you can collect from people just driving
a car which type of data you actually
need from the car that you prepare that
are driving themselves so think about
like a fleet of driving car like level 4
well like if you are trying to learn to
drive on data you can you can gather
this data from simply like people
driving around they don't need to be
driving with your own car you need to
make sure that they have enough sensor
and the sensor representative off of the
car that you plant eventually to Elise
for your for your final system but you
can distinguish between your fleet that
you use for testing to test your
algorithm it that are driving themselves
versus the fleet that you just used for
data collection so even if you are like
working level for example in tracking
you don't need to have like self-driving
tracking on the old in order to be able
to collect data from tracking you can
like retrofit existing tracking with the
right sensors and learn how to drive
from manual from people that are
actually driving just to stocks so yeah
I think doing that distinction could
help like getting into like the segment
where it's a little are them to be like
big big networks and there's we've seen
automation go into agriculture first and
see having a large area you know
good opportunity for development know
some software stuff is so needs to get
worked out yes right to repair culture
is a great example of automation that's
easier than driving because the safety
aspect of it is not is not like Samantha
but it's a good example yeah how
automation works and then we talked for
the last few days about having the right
kind of sample set
how different are the videos and how
applicable are the models from the
different driving style so people in New
York Drive very different than people
here places like Georgia we have the
long commute like Houston so what is
their prioritization yeah that's a good
question so for level two like for what
we do I mean with more variety we get
from data the better we try to be the
system is somewhat works decently in
pretty much like every driving condition
if you try to build something like a
fleet of level 4 vehicles I think you
should focus on your first application
so if your first application is a system
that is going to service people like in
a suburban place where like speed is
limited maybe like to 30 miles per 30 5
miles per hour and like there is not
like huge traffic then maybe you should
like focus on collecting data from those
aisles because those represent your
first like go to market application and
you shouldn't try to some sort of like
mixing with data that's coming from
environment that are outside the scope
of the first release of your product so
it really depends I would say like if
you're focusing a level for now don't
trying to get data from New York try to
try to focus on where where you're gonna
have your first application and it's now
going to be New York and we'd also
talked about the applicability of car
videos being used for like larger Class
eight vehicles you know camera it's
going to look different even for your
modeling so that's a good thing there's
a lot of data out there and micro
processors have gotten cheap super
although your cloud storage bill might
go up a bit
yes definitely like due to the sensors
i've super each output like a cameras
like you think about the stream of
camera
it's like mega mega mega pixels and so
think about how much data that is sure
you can compress your video but still
like we are talking about i mean in our
case like our device collects pretty
much between 5 and gigabytes of data per
hour if you talk about like level 4 you
are probably talking about like a
gigabyte per hour collected by your
system and so yes I mean like processing
this data becomes like feasible now on
like real time but at the same time if
you're storing this data you have to
think about how expensive is going to be
your your storage bill when you are like
uploading all these data to your to your
servers you know how can you know if
you're interested in in working with you
know autonomous vehicles and car tech
the the problem presents a good
opportunity for developing new models
for we saw some models for that the our
CNN with picture refinement and
different ways to classify images so
you're closer to it so you know how are
different ways to get in to be involved
or the other development opportunities
that aren't necessarily in the card type
you know yeah well so self-driving cars
are mainly like a software problem it's
not really a problem that has been some
sort of like I see solved I and I see it
like I really frame it as a software as
a possible problem how do we how do we
make like a robot that they can drive as
human or can at least like assist human
driving so yeah you don't need to be
caressed better to be involved you need
amino free to have like passion for for
software and that there are like many
aspects of it you can you can work on
machine learning you can work on
planning controls that management
infrastructure there are really really a
lot of aspect about it that people like
engineers can can get can getting ball
to it
I mean if somebody's interested into
into getting more involved about it
we have like all our software it's open
source like comedy I makes all the
software open source it's called open
pilot you can go and get add you can
read the application you can read the
how our software start works and that
software is software that supports the
Arbour that we sell which is called the
comedy khmer on so the other that we
sell is a smart dash cam and if you
you're interested into being like a
developer and learning more about
solving car so you can actually put the
two things together and you can have
like a level to retrofit that cell
driving car which is the one that I
showed in the video and everybody can
imagine the the adjacent industries and
even the service industries as people's
mobility patterns and habits changed
they've already changed first with lift
and now you can get anything delivered
to your house so that opens up as we're
talking fleet slates have come up a few
times either how could your business be
changed by it is there some different
model that we're seeing you know be
thinking of this when thinking of a
tongue which I'm sure everybody has been
thinking of it to be it the impact of
autonomous vehicles to your business but
fleets and adjacent services are
interesting the utilization rate yeah
yeah definitely they want one good thing
about the Thomas vague like driverless
vehicle is that they respected like
utility sure it is gonna be much higher
than any of the car existing which we
really think about like the trucking
industry the trucking industry when when
we are gonna see 11 4 trucks on their
order
well tracking is going to become like
radically different because you're not
gonna be any more constrained by the
maximum I think it's eight hours like
maximum continues driving from from
driver so you can have those trucks like
driving pretty much like no staff but
for for as long as it takes to go from
point A to point B and so yeah certain
industries and I really look forward to
tracking industries are gonna be
radically changed by a for example you
to musicians right other things are
gonna change I would expect like
the first application I'll add before
being I there is gonna be a company that
owns the fleet like I do really see
especially because at the beginning
there is gonna be a lot of like
iterations like on they are on the
services of the maintenance there are a
lot of like unknowns and so I do see
making sense that there is gonna be like
a company that owns the fleet as opposed
a little as opposed to what we see today
with uber drivers where it's very
distributed single drivers that own
their car and contribute to the fleet
instead I rather see those fleet being
directly managed and central is the by
the company that provides the service
and it's upgrading is a bigger deal with
the these smarter cars getting software
updates and good have to happen fleet
management makes more sense and that can
make a lot of sense in that context yeah
exactly what I was mentioning like there
is this need of being like closely
connected with your fleet being able to
upgrade your car so and especially like
at the beginning so definitely it's
gonna be like the first implementation
it's gonna be like our own fleet does
anybody know the utilization rate for a
consumer car unless you're like an uber
driver because that's or you know in
your car yeah I've heard you end up not
using your car its parts around 90
percent of the time whereas you can kind
of flip that model with an autonomous
vehicle in delivery services you can
have like at last mile issues you
actually might need to have a human
doing some interaction but again you
know looking for ways you can interact
with this new vendor industry that's
that is something if there's not a
driver in the car how would your
business work with them and serve them
so would that change anything any aspect
of what you're doing now let's see how
about consumer adoption of babies well
so okay if we talk about level two it
really something there it's it's hard to
convey so you just I just have an idea
like how many of you have been in a
level to sell driving car like raise
your hand if you have been why I would
say it's like temperature
10% of you have been like in 11 - well
consider that there are 0.2% of cars 11
- on the road today so 10% yeah you this
audience definitely got a good exposure
to them and it's something that you need
to experience you need to realize how
better your driving can be and how safe
it can be because you are basically
relieved by the stress of constantly
having to interact with your car making
sure that you're keeping the proper
distance with the car ahead of you also
a car drives itself as a much shorter
reaction time because like you have a
computer like watching the road and
taking actions and then at the same time
you have a monitoring system it
constantly reminds that you have to pay
attention and I mean it's debated there
are certain I mean there are voices that
say this is actually going to be harder
to manage from the driver because it's
gonna push people to get more distracted
I've been driving these systems I've
been developing this system and
everybody that I talk to that has been
like an elaborate systems as a political
opinion about how level-2 can actually
like improve people's people striving so
I think it's something like the man will
grow as the offer will grow as more and
more cars we pushed or three would be
will be keeping level two systems I
think the acceptance rate is going to
grow as a consequence I would say for
eleventh for I I think it's gonna be
literally like a question of costs as I
said before
11400 really exists and you can you can
be driven from point A to point B
without having to drive it's just a
matter of can I offer something that is
like practical can bring it up from
point A to point B we eventually same
amount or less time and the same cost or
less if that's true then acceptance rate
or like level four it's gonna be is
gonna be mad it's gonna it's gonna
happen otherwise they're not gonna
succeed and it's not populace that is
gonna be the case definitely I don't see
it being the case for quite a bit so the
National Highway Transportation Safety
Administration has been a proponent of
some of these these driver assist
because they save lives like the safer
you can make cars I think that helps me
work through acceptance of like letting
my
Siri yell at me about staying in my lane
just as the balance of you know
inattention does you know accidents
happen when people are not paying
attention so I think that's gonna help
be at least a driver for it and it's
definitely a messaging what he needs to
do definitely I did the safety aspect is
very important I think there is a huge
opportunity for level truth to make a
car safer that the starting point is not
greater like Fattal accidents are the
number one cause of death among young
people between age 16 and 24 and they
represent about like two percent because
of death worldwide so there's definitely
a big opportunity there to make a car
safer and smarter regarding 11-4 there
is a little bit like nah I see a lot of
like unfair comparison when we talk
about safety related to level four
because what what one of the thing that
is being said when when you people like
talked about that before is oh well it's
gonna be a lot safer but again you don't
have to compare 11 4 with like you
driving the car you have to compare
level 4 with the services it's level Pro
compete with which is public
transportation which is the driver which
if you take aware I would say it's very
like another of magnitude safer then you
drive your car if anything because is
offering your service and is paying more
attention that if you weren't in the car
so when you talk about safety for level
4 you need to contesta lies it and
comparable to a poll which I don't see
it done like very often while in level 2
well you need to be better than people
to have in the car after is earlier yes
great question I think
see any potential for complacency on if
you're at level two for too long before
technology hits level four does the
average driver out there that's tweeting
looking at Facebook on their computers
become complacent and get distracted you
see accident rates going higher than you
anticipate it's currently level two
drivers they know they're in a test law
they know they're supposed to be in
acting so they're participating more if
the lag between level two and level four
is years do you see that people will
trust too much in the increase in
accident rates no I think it's actually
going the other way around I think like
people that get into level two cars
today are more confused about this
technology probably are not completely
aware of the technology one thing that I
I wish Tesla was doing that it doesn't
and actually we do is driver monitoring
so how do we actually be monitor that
the driver is paying attention that's a
good way to like educate on this part
about what's the proper behavior to take
when you're on a level 2 car you have to
pay attention and yeah I mean if you
have like camera watching the driver Jen
does that once with supercruise there is
like a video camera an infrared camera
that looks at you and can tell you if
you start and we do the same thing and I
think this is very important so as we
move forward I think there will be as
the acceptance and understanding of what
leverage system is I think like drivers
and users will be better educated
because they understand what so no I
don't I I expect that over time things
are actually gonna get things people are
gonna be better educated than they
currently are and not to be punitive
that I think the other thing that
naturally comes from that as the drivers
are monitors you know that would be
introduced as evidence in a court case
at some point so I think knowing that
you have a camera on you
also will affect you know your
interaction with it not just you know
fall asleep on the 405 hopefully well I
mean yeah I mean it really depends like
I'm currently done we don't collect
people's people's face unless they
consent to and they Yelp I was like
training driver monitoring models
somebody needs to actively
santé to be able to for us to record
their data otherwise we just provide the
feature but we now record the data but
yes definitely yes okay so I hope I can
ask this question properly but if I'm
Ford and what how will I be adopting all
of this so what will it look like so
you're saying today Tesla is the only
company that has this software update
well all cars have that what will Ford
be doing over the next 10 years what
will their production look like to be
able to start adopting this what do you
think I can say because I I'm in the
industry so and I've seen Toyota's been
doing partnerships with uber on both
autonomous TVs and retrofitting like
Siena's so like a regular internal
combustion engine cars and what what I'm
seeing evidence of is they're hedging
their bets it might move this way it
might go way more electric you know is
the supply chain to support you know a
more electric car part in place but they
they have for years although they might
not be on the road there they are doing
R&D and and I'm not just saying for Ford
I'm saying in general for the car
manufacturers we're seeing them partner
there they've started forming alliances
you can start seeing different clusters
of ones that are working with others so
I don't think they have the full answer
yet but at least we were level four for
the different levels of development they
have been investing money in that so
yeah then we let us see it like I I
don't know what they are waiting for
officially because I mean if you think
about that like for software Ricola
they have like let's say you have a
software glitch and a tap and it have
been lagging Toyota's like several times
I compress right so you have the other
software Ricola and the software recall
you have to recall millions of cars how
much of a cost is that like quantifies
that it's like hundreds of millions if
you have to recall like millions of cars
that's the equivalent of money that you
have to spend for software update and
then also like the development cycle
your learning cycle is much longer right
so you I mean when you're at least like
the fact that you can do so over here
update does
mean that what you learn is isn't safe
right so you need to work out the safety
part of your software before you release
it and that part doesn't change but then
I would say there is like an extra
probably 70% that is just like user
interface things that are not safety
critical that if there is a glitch is
not the end of the war that you can work
out those making updates over the air so
how much shorter will the different
cycle be if you don't need like to test
for so many hours the fact that if you
click a button the the proper answer on
UI happens right for example so I don't
need to understand what they're waiting
for
but the actual answer is I mean like
this company is very good at making cars
making reliable cars they have a little
B to invent themselves if they want to
be up to date wait we sort of problem
it's an infrastructure problem that you
have to build and it's something new so
but there you have to do it if they want
to be relevant if they want to survive
they have to get in today so that why
it's like there is no way to compete
with the other companies that actually
are making this a possibility there is
like there's a huge cost opportunity
there there's a lot of value and people
doing what they excel at companies too
so if you're awesome at making cars you
know partner with people who are awesome
at the technology problem Karl yeah just
I want to return back to this the
concept of safety as you move through
the different levels here you talk
extensively about that what are some of
the the AI approaches that are being
developed to address adversarial type of
threats to smart vehicles for example I
you know you can have like obstruction
of signage for example and trick a
vehicle
thinking that oh that's not a stop sign
so I'm gonna go right by so what are
some of the solutions in the AI space
that is being explored to make sure that
as you move through those levels yeah
about time is it that these vehicles are
getting smarter and not so susceptible
to tricks and adversarial tax definitely
so I mean like the problem gets a lot
easier the more mice you can
collect because you have the choice of
deciding which which they thought a
favor so for example like as a show
during the presentation the large
majority of data you collect from from
cars so if you don distinguish the one
that is good anyone that is did one that
is use from the one is not is like
boring data it's like you driving on
there is not much to learn after certain
point and so yes you need to favor those
events that are somewhat events from
which you can learn so like having a
horror mystery Bhushan of your data that
are represented by by specific events
from which you can learn and you can do
that in many ways like one way that you
can do it is like mark every
intervention that the try like if you
have your system that is like a level
two system every time that the user
intervenes to correct the car it's
somewhat like a disengagement is
somewhat like something that they can be
didn't do right and so you can actually
collect those event in favor of those
events to learn something specific that
well so the first one learning is a
little bit yes when first learning well
that's important if a like a personal
learning in the sense that you deploy
something and you use like the user as
so sort of like your feedback there is
some sort of like ethical aspect to it
that should be you can see that because
you're using like the user as you're
like reinforcement loop but in a certain
sense it's fair to do it as long as like
what you released at any given time is
safe no more interesting like you can do
it for smell owning like completely like
offline so you can you can train your
model planner a personal learning so you
tap you set up like a simulator like we
doing that come and you make the card
learning from from reinforcement
learning system so you generate the data
so you you generate situation where you
put the car in a situation where it
shouldn't be and you learn from that it
straight it's not it's not a simple
thing but we have like good approaches
or calm that we that we are
investigating and we actually like using
right now on on models that we are
deploying
yes
so I know you've been asked this
probably a hundred times before and this
question is not new at all but I'm
interested on your take on it
so the safety issue if you have a car
and there are pedestrians and the car
has to decide if it's going to crash to
save the pedestrians or the people in
the car or maybe a way to crash to save
the people in the car and the front
versus the back how would a car make
that decision great so you're right I've
been asked a lot of times about this and
the answer is IIIi don't think it's like
very very relevant problem at the moment
like it's not at the point where like
this kind of decision matters and also I
don't think it's very relevant even if
we were at that point I think the answer
is very relevant at the point that you
may need like a car that is like driving
safer than a human like the sort of
decisions are really down the point
where they don't matter I don't see such
like I don't see it even from an ethical
point of view I don't see it being like
that like let the engineer on the side
like as long as the overall output
system is like safer it does not really
matter like what what would a human do
right the only reason why we don't ask
this question to human is because we
think that it's happening fasting after
the human doesn't have to think about it
but so what would a human do let's say
you have enough time to think about it
in some case you might have enough time
to think about this situation what would
a human do and I would say another
possible answer is well how to prevent
this sort of situation beforehand so you
want we want to be able to minimize as
much as possible situation where you
have no good options
so that would be step one and then step
two is like I mean like what do you mean
I think it's not a girl question that
applies to robust I think it's a legal
question that like could could apply to
you man if you want ask the question I
think I know during startup we drive a I
did a presentation and that question
came up there and for their models they
trained to stop so like even if it
doesn't have to be an immediate safety
thing and this is it was in limited
deployment but it was to take the car
safely to a stop before they got to
where it was collision closed
yes well our complaints is already it's
already happened it's not it's not full
automation but like I would say like
planes are the closest thing to what we
intend as level to level to driver like
Suzanne driving cars in agriculture
already happened why do you have these
like big tractors doing doing the field
work without human assistance ships I'm
not an expert in ships but I would say
that yeah most of the ship work can be
done without a human constant like
interacting with it and there are
probably like good warning systems to
avoid colliding with icebergs and other
fields like train I'm trained already
like people automated like me to meet
metals there are like me it was like um
it was don't even and like I Drive like
a Macanese like a person that stays
stays in physically looking into it
being into the into the metal itself and
into the path so yeah I mean it's
already happened I think it's gonna
happen and it's already happen sooner in
other fields before it's gonna happen in
so dragon capsule so I think also
probably gonna be like the tail of of
these things which is why when we talk
about like level 5 this idea of having
like a curve it has complete itself
without the assistance of a human as
well as a human boon it's not something
that it's gonna happen without us
noticing it it's gonna be I think at the
tail of many how they are filled that
are gonna be automated first so we're
gonna know when we're gonna be close to
level 5 we will know it if we now we
don't know it means that we're not close
I think one good thing that comes out of
it though is a lot of the technology
used to detect things and solve problems
in
to end up cars can be used for assisted
technology on other modes of
transportation so they've already had
kind of independent aids that can help
you know people navigate who are
mobility challenged so I think that is
one just ninth nice natural consequence
of the development that's happening in
your space
so obviously you as a company and all
companies will have tremendous
tremendous incentive to make it an
accident free environment because one
accident is going to drive your share
price down so that will necessarily
limit what your car will allow the
passenger to want to do so if I want to
speed in my own car and I'm driving I
have the full autonomy to do whatever I
want and I'm taking my full risk when
the decision is is delegated to the car
manufacturer they have the the incentive
to minimize accidents at the expense of
individual passenger or owner autonomy
can you express your opinion on that
yeah I mean I think like people
shouldn't speed and I mean say I don't
see why cars like and we are able to go
up to 100 miles per hour
like if the max limit is like 70 like
let's say 7 let's say 80 miles per hour
I can limit the speed of 80 miles per
hour like the large majority of
accidents are caused because people are
driving in a way they're not supposed to
drive so limiting the the way that the
car is capable of what the carriage
capable of doing is not a limit to
freedom of like owner of the car to
drive the car it's actually like a smart
thing to do but I want also like comment
on the first thing that you said which
is like one accident the for autonomous
vehicle is gonna be very bad and it's
gonna there is a need to push for
accident phrase well I mean perfect is
the worst enemy of good right so let's
focus where we are now and let's try to
make things better let's not
overemphasize of
yes there's gonna be accidents but we
have a lot of accidents now we need to
make something that is better than now
if we if we if we emphasize too much
like for example we do with planes when
there is a like a plane accident we
emphasize it too much then people are
gonna have this like over a perception
for what safety is and yeah we need to
avoid we to do our best to avoid to get
into these like force perception that
some driving her are not gonna be safe
because we are worth a lot about one
accident we have to wait it with actual
data actual numbers we have to wait it
with the 37,000 fatalities that happen
each year in US and so yeah I think I
think we need to have a database
approach when when we talk about safety
and it's very important that we push for
that yes so you're talking about an
autonomous vehicle is there any
development that a vehicle is part of a
network and they will exchange
information like intent what a car like
intent what a car is going to do it's
going to turn alright and then other
cars no so you're talking like vehicle
to vehicle communication exactly I have
two traffic lights or whatever yes okay
so I I think it's different things I
think one of them is good one of them is
now going to happen so what is now going
to happen I think is very good a
communication the problem with a connect
to communication are public I would say
to one problem is it's gonna be very
hard to make every car manufacturer to
agree on a protocol of communication I
just don't see this happening like so
which type of the ATAG an exchange
because like you basically need to may
have many developers agreeing on a
common standard and also I don't see it
being necessary like you understand what
the other car is doing by observing
other car you don't need to know in
advance of what the other guy is going
to do and also like how do you trust
like you are not the developer like if
you're talking about they convey
communication between your cars probably
you can do something but you're not
going to have a fee that is large enough
to be relevant and to be something you
can rely on so if you have to rely on
somebody else development of like
attributes like in
path accelerations those things that are
not even simple to measure and to
predict in the future
well imagine trusting not something to
battle but trusting somebody that
somebody has developed so I don't think
even if it was the case I don't think
this being being useful like I don't see
I don't see one thing that instead I do
see happening is vehicle to
infrastructure communication between v2
ax so v2 action genera like this idea
that like the car needs some information
from the first structure so for example
like traffic light you want to optimize
for traffic you want to optimize for
like going from A to B you want to know
the state of for example of traffic
lights and so yeah you can know that but
that's different because there is like a
manufacturer or that makes the standard
and then it's up to the car developers
again to a standard that they didn't
have to admit to the Indonesia start to
comply with so that's that's a little
bit easier to push under standard and
also I see it being useful
I see like yeah I mean knowing in
advance informations that's useful and I
mean a certain size it's already
happening like v2 acts like if you want
to know like I mean like your GPS
position like in some senses be two acts
right
you're you are you are communicating
with with satellite so it's just an
evolution of what's already here yes
so standards for inter communication
already exist in the development world
why do you think it would be different
for autonomous vehicles like well why do
you think developers were in create come
together and create a set of standards
that they can develop on well because I
mean fundamentally there is really no so
I mean the death like a reason I mean I
saying yes you can be standard part of a
communication but if there is no I
really need for that like a real
advantage there's another reason for
that not to happen so it's two of the
course not only one so again on
something is not the course not being
useful he's another obstacles if you put
these two things together that's why I
see is not going to happen for for
because I'm not saying it's impossible
to agree on
as I'm saying that if there is not to be
like a big push for it it's not going to
happen
yeah I think if you like you people I
mean the companies should invest not
like understanding environment
understanding what other cars are doing
but it what are their like players on
the environment are doing based on what
you observe from them rather than having
them telling you what's like it's gonna
happen my work okay for cars but what
about cyclists what about pedestrians
and those are like equivalently are the
players on this on on the film like on
the environment that you have to deal
with and so yeah even if you if you
could help it's not something you can
rely entirely because not this
information cannot even come from all
the players in the environment security
measures you guys have been taking not
to hack your software yeah so I mean
like okay so you know when you develop
systems for for like level two is
different than when you al when you
develop like safety systems from level
two in abhava when we develop system for
like level two the driver is always
responsible in the end and so you need
to make sure that every action that the
car takes in autonomy is never gonna be
too abrupt to make the driver are not
capable of really taking control of the
vehicle if they if the car is something
wrong so by doing this you're limiting
for example the amount of like the
operational domain of your actuators
some example like the braking system you
need to make sure that your braking
system is never gonna command too much
braking deceleration because if you are
mistakenly braking when you shouldn't
think you are driving a highway at high
speed then you can cause an accident so
the way that you make the system saves
for level two is you limit your
operational domain what that translates
into is you are making a system that by
design is now going to be able to handle
100 percent of the mice that you drive
to give you like some numbers like
people that drive with the tez autopilot
from Statistics some people from the
University of MIT collected a large data
form from a fleet that they monitored
and thirdly I think it's 32 percent of
the miles driven are driven with
autopilot on for us for people to drive
with open pilot it's 52 percent we are
working towards the 80 percent maybe 85
we know we are not like by design of a
level system is now gonna get to other
percent there are certain environment
where if you have the cooperating in
autonomy there it's just not going to be
safe because in order to be able to
drive in this environment the car is
taking actions that you might not be
able to retake control quick enough for
example taking like 90 degree turns in
an environment where there are a lot of
pedestrian around like this is not a
place where lever to system if you want
to work environment you need level any
party no I think I mean like I would say
I
I recommend like if you want to get
involved with it a little bit more with
comma go on comedy our website or go on
our key time explore our code see what
we do and see what is like our approach
of trying to make the existing fleet of
cars smarter than what they are now
[Applause]